<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>John Dutton's, alias Prince Dutton's farewel to Temple-Bar. Licensed, June 19th, 1694</title>
            <author>Dutton, John, fl. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81937</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897576</idno>
  <idno type="VID">132837</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240933539</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2909B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224526</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897576</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99897576e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2513:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>John Dutton's, alias Prince Dutton's farewel to Temple-Bar. Licensed, June 19th, 1694</title>
                  <author>Dutton, John, fl. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold at the Golden Fleece in Fleetstreet, over against the Inner-Temple-Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Dutton, John, fl. 1694 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:1"/>
            <p>John Duttons, ALIAS <hi>Prince Dutton's</hi> FAREWEL TO TEMPLE-BAR.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Licensed,</hi>
                           <date>June 19th, 1694.</date>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold at the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> over against the <hi>Inner-Temple-Gate.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:2"/>
            <head>THE Epistle Dedicatory,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To all the Students in Lewdness and Debauchery.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Having made it my whole Practise in this stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Science, what I have found most agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Nature, and that which hath given the most lengthening Satisfaction; I having studied every individual, pleasant, agreeable means, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, object and fancy, not omiting any thing that could be thought necessary to fulfil the desired pleasure; and having had the Theorick, as well as the Practick, I have acquired to be a Master of Art in this Function, that, that as the Learned calls <hi>Momentary,</hi> I have by Artificial manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, lengthened many minutes; but was forc't at last to part with, as the Old Man did with his Pillow, rousing up the Spirits, and then with a Hem, or Sigh, give way to a momentary Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity; but by the heat and scirculation of the Blood, and every Vital being in motion, quickly recovered to the true sence of considering what
<pb facs="tcp:132837:3"/> was so lately past; and the true and just Merits thereof, where I was confused with the anxiety and disorder of the mind, to think of the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to my Maker in the Offence, when I had a Lawful means to lay this Itch; this caused such a smarting in my Conscience, when I came to a true consideration, how God Almighty has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly punisht them or him according to his own Heart, and that may be for only one sin; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what can we expect that have been guilty of as many as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomora;</hi> therefore to you Gentlemen, that are most Culpable, consider the cause of my Disorder, being come to my self, and desiring to be a true Penitent, with a hearty Contrition and resolution of amendment, desir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the assistance of all the Angels, that we read, <hi>do rejoyce at the Repentance of a sinner;</hi> so, not only wishing, but Praying for your following of my resolved Reformation, which is the humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of him that is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most obedient Servant<lb/>
                  <hi>John Dutton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF I shall gain any Applause in this undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I think it convenient to be so grateful, in the first place, to my Maker, from whom I have received Breath; in the next, not to be unmindful of my Education; First, from my Parents; then from whose Works and Conversation I have most Profited in. In my Nature, from the beginning, I was ever true to my Friend, many times to a fault; I ever was an Enemy to all Servants where I ever lived that were not true in their Practise and Trust; It was always my Temper to give every Creature its intrinsick value, even the very Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and Vegitable. I had, when I came to years of Ʋnderstanding, an inclination to Learning; and
<pb facs="tcp:132837:4"/> my Pious Mother designed me for Travel, which I had an inclination to; but my Mother Dying the year after the Restoring of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that was prevented, my Father having six of us to take care of, only some Goods left, an Estate newly retreived from the Rebels, lost again by her Death. I received no farther Schooling than my <hi>Grammer;</hi> in <hi>Arithmatick, Division;</hi> So my Father told me I must think of some Trade, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Eldest; in which Trade I was so forward, that before I had been two years at it, my Father left me at that Antient, Honourable Family, the late Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury's</hi> at <hi>Grafton</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestershire,</hi> Master Cook, where many Weeks our Kitchen Expence amounted to Thirty Pound a Week; our yearly Expence was one large Ox a Week, besides all other Meats; our setled Family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upwards of Sixty in Family. When I came to settle in the World for my self, I came acquainted with Mr. <hi>Thomas Hall,</hi> a very good City Cook, and the only sensible Man of the Trade, who was a great Sufferer for being a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> (I being the same) at all leisure times I used to Visit him, where I found the greatest <hi>satisfaction</hi> in <hi>Conversation,</hi> and came acquainted with many good Books, and Knowledg in them; and I have many
<pb facs="tcp:132837:4"/> now by me, that I have been offered double what they cost me. The next of my Delights has been <hi>Heraclitus Ridens.</hi> But the most Worthy and ever to be Honoured Sir <hi>Roger L'Estrange</hi> his Works, for both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human Practice;</hi> how to avoid the drawing on (not forgotten) Miseries in matters of State particularly. So as the whole Work is but short, I will trouble you with no more, but Pray for my Bennifactors in general; and I hope you will accept the Will for the Deed, if there be any mistakes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your well wisher, and<lb/> Humble Servant<lb/>
                  <hi>John Dutton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:5"/>
            <head>John Duttons, ALIAS <hi>Prince Dutton's</hi> FAREWEL TO TEMPLE-BAR.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From amongst the <hi>Lunaticks</hi> at Dr. <hi>Adam</hi>'s House, over-against the <hi>Kings Head</hi> in <hi>Marybone,</hi>
                     <date>April 26. 1694.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Neighbours, and Fellow-Mechanicks,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THIS is to give you the True Reasons for my withdrawing my self from my House at the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Loaf</hi> within <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> after Two Months Confinement amongst distempered People, and parting with the best and loyalist of Wives, and Six most Dutiful Children, which at this time are Extraordinary Jewels.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:132837:6"/>
               <p>In the first place, I think it convenient to inquire into the Original and Natural Causes of my differing from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of our Mechanicks, especially those Greesie ones the <hi>Cooks</hi> in general.</p>
               <p>In the first place, by my Father's side I am a Spawn of that Ancient Family of the <hi>Duttons</hi> in <hi>Cheshire;</hi> and the <hi>Beaumounts</hi> of <hi>Leistershire;</hi> On my Mothers side, the <hi>White</hi>'s of <hi>Dorsetshire,</hi> and <hi>Turgis</hi>'s of <hi>Ringwood</hi> in <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> which the <hi>Whites</hi> especially of <hi>Fittlefoord,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> had an Estate of One Thousand Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> before his late High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>'s Usurpation, my Family being <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks,</hi> and Actors for King <hi>Charles</hi> the First, in that Unnatural and Inhumane War, in which we had All taken from us for our <hi>Loyalty;</hi> for which my Father had in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Time some small acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Crown.</p>
               <p>My Father being bred up in the Family of the Lord <hi>Chouerths</hi> of <hi>Ansley,</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamshire;</hi> there being a most plentiful House for Hospitality, it then being much in Fashion in this Kingdom; His Delight being most in the Kitchen, the then Lord <hi>Clouerth</hi> caused him to be put an Apprentice to one <hi>Duffel,</hi> a <hi>Cook,</hi> in <hi>Fetter-lane.</hi> When he was near out of his Time, he being very forward in his business, Sir <hi>John Webb</hi> of <hi>Canfoord Magna,</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorset,</hi> bought out the Residue of his Time. He had not lived long there before he came acquainted with Mrs. <hi>Ann White,</hi> the Daughter of Mr. <hi>William White,</hi> then Steward to Sir <hi>John Webb,</hi> whom he married against the Father's Consent; she being the Only Child
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132837:6"/> left, and in them Days a Considerable Fortune, and a fine Woman, and very Young.</p>
               <p>This happening presently after the beheading of that good K. <hi>Charles</hi> the First, he took my Mother to <hi>London,</hi> to settle in the Trade he was bred up in, and took an House in <hi>Drury-lane,</hi> near St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the Fields. My Mother being then with Child of me, he was but just well setled, when there came out an Order from his late Highness St. <hi>Oliver,</hi> to banish all <hi>Cavaliers</hi> from within Ten Miles of <hi>London;</hi> which forced my Father to leave the Town, he having been in the Kings Army as long as the Wars lasted, and left my Mother behind in <hi>London,</hi> to make the best of the House and Goods; she being forc'd to go to her disobliged Parents, and my Father to go to a Family of the <hi>Carells</hi> in <hi>Sussex</hi> to Service; in which Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice my Father continued some Time; I being in that Time born; and had the Honour to be a Foster-Brother to some of that Family, my Mother giving a Child of that Family part of my Milk, when I became able to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
               <p>I had my first Education amongst the Children of the late Sir <hi>John Webb,</hi> a Family we have all been much oblig'd to, to this Day, I having a Sister living at this time there, which received her whole Education from them.</p>
               <p>When the Clouds began to disperse, and <hi>Old Nick</hi> came in a Tempest for his true Friend and Benefactor <hi>Old Noll;</hi> my Father then went to serve the Honourable Mr. <hi>Thomas Arundel,</hi> that married that Worthy Lady Madam <hi>Lucy,</hi> of <hi>Sutton Park</hi> in <hi>Worcestershire,</hi> where he sent for me, and put me to School to a very good Master in the Church of <hi>Tenbury,</hi> in the same County, where a Bridge parts this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132837:7"/> County and <hi>Shropshire.</hi> Then came that merry, musical Time of the <hi>Restoration</hi> of our Exil'd Prince; <hi>Charles</hi> the Second. Then I saw nothing but Mirth, Good Hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>Maurice-Dancing,</hi> and all sorts of Old <hi>English</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, with such a Dinn of <hi>Restoration,</hi> that I cannot drive it out of my Head ever since.</p>
               <p>At this place I came in Fancy of <hi>Cookery,</hi> there being always for the Time of my Father's living, Open House kept, especially at the Festival Times of the Year, where I was an Eye-Witness, and withal had a Finger in the Pye; and seeing such daily great Gifts come to my Father, and such great Profits allowed, and Priviledges to <hi>Cooks,</hi> that although my Father preffered me the choice of any Trade yet nothing would serve me but that; which I often repented, until now, that I am become Master of it, altho in an ignorant Age for Judges, especially amongst the Young Gallants; For if One of the Gang bleats, <hi>That there is a New House Open, and the best in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>at Cookery, and came from such a place;</hi> That <hi>the Master thereof, to my Knowledge,</hi> never <hi>rightly</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it; Away they run, like so many <hi>Sheep to the Fold,</hi> or <hi>Pens;</hi> and <hi>there is One Sauce for All Meats;</hi> like <hi>the Quack-Dostors, One Pill for All Distempers.</hi> Then crys One Fopp <hi>'This Fellow works himself, and such an one is always abroad.</hi> Then crys another <hi>Shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, He is so dear, I will not go there;</hi> That is, in plain Terms, because <hi>He is indebted to me.</hi> The next of my Calumniators, and Detracters, crys, <hi>He says in his Drinking, he can spend with a Man of Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds a Year, and break him, says this Villain, that has often eat at my cost: We must needs expect to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132837:7"/> be cheated if we go there: Therefore what is all this but pretended Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Ʋngrateful Returns for Civilities shown;</hi> when I intend to oblige them, that should not make a Wrong Construction of Favours <hi>receiv'd.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore This is Enough to set a man upon <hi>the Extream Resolution</hi> of Old <hi>Timon</hi> of <hi>Athens,</hi> that resolv'd to be an Hater of All Mankind, for their <hi>Ingratitude.</hi> But my next Entertainment shall be according to <hi>Timon</hi>'s; that is, <hi>Empty Dishes.</hi> But as I have found <hi>some friends in need,</hi> both Men and Women; it is, and always was my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to give all mankind their just due, both in Debt and Character; and wherever I have received a signal Kindness, I never did, nor never shall think I have made a grateful Return; not as I set forth this small Paper to Justify my self, but that there is many Traders now liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near me, that I have dealt withal, and my Family still deals with, who have received many thousands of Pounds of me, and many others in the several Markets in and about <hi>London;</hi> and I boldly Challenge any of them, whether they can, or ever could charge me with any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just Action in my way of Trading between Man and Man; if they can, I desire they would make it as pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lick as I have this; or if I ever offered to pay less than <hi>Twenty Shillings in the Pound;</hi> nor ever was it my Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to bate any man, without I found his Bill very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable; but on the contrary, to the lessening my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, when I liv'd in that unfortunate place to me, <hi>White-Fryars,</hi> where I first set up to Trade for my self, being incouraged by the Customers, I having lived one year in the House before I took it, with the best of Mistresses, but the worst, the miserablest, and uncharitablest of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132837:8"/> Landladies that ever an Honest meaning Man had to do withal, although promised me other things, which you that read this shall Judg.</p>
               <p>I first took a Thorn out of her Foot, and put it into my own, in taking a Lease in that place for one and twenty years, and paying down one Hundred and Fifty Pounds Fine, and Sixty Three Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> and had not above two years Trade that deserved that Rent; I entered upon this when I was Twenty Pounds in Debt, which no man could have done without the sum of Five Hundred Pounds of good and lawful Mony of <hi>England,</hi> entered clearly to Trade, and go to Market with ready Mony; but having the promise of one Hundred and Fifty Pounds from my Father, I ventured to begin upon Credit; I having the prospect of a good House well Customed, not unknown to many of their Greasinesses, that were then Sages and Governours of that Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, many of them now living, who then thought I had a very hard bargain.</p>
               <p>I kept the House one whole year a Batchelour, then thought it high time to take a Yoak-mate; I having se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Offers, but none that I could really like so well as she that is my present Wife, with whom I was in Love four years before; I could have had one with six Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds, I being then Indebted Five Hundred; but none could please me but this, altho she had but two Hundred; and she has proved so good, that what she wanted in Fortune, she has made up in Goodness, that I may say more than many can, <hi>that I never yet repented my Bargain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:132837:8"/>
               <p>Then came that famous Crew of <hi>Monarchy-Hunters,</hi> into great Voge, that never to be forgotten Doctor <hi>O. Tongue, Bedlow,</hi> and many more of those Saints, <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory, Tantivy-men,</hi> and such like distinctions, which I look upon to be the procursors of our late Disorders; these times were very prejudicial to me and other innocent People; I being then Cook to that Honourable Society of <hi>Serjants Inn</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet;</hi> and the last Dinner that I drest for them, was the Consecration of their Chappel; the present B. of <hi>London</hi> Preached the Sermon; where I had the honour of <hi>Thanks</hi> for what I had done, and about the Sum of <hi>Forty Pounds</hi> paid me for the <hi>Dinner,</hi> and all that ever I did for them, honestly Paid, with an <hi>Expression of Pity</hi> from that True <hi>Friend</hi> Mr. Serjeant <hi>Goodfellow,</hi> then Treasurer of that House, <hi>That I was not a Protestant, if I had, I might have injoyed the place.</hi> This and a great deal more I suffered at that time for my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> and since which I must Challenge many of my Perswasion that I know living at this time, that swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Oaths, and appeared at the Church to save their Bacon, which I thank God I never did, nor never will for <hi>Interest</hi> sake; and all them that did, or ever do, I look upon them to be no better than Hypocrites, and a greater <hi>Scandal to the Church</hi> than I have been in all my <hi>Frolicks;</hi> mine being caused by <hi>Trouble</hi> and <hi>Loss,</hi> and in the <hi>Passion</hi> of <hi>Drinking</hi> and <hi>Disorder;</hi> theirs Premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</p>
               <p>Now times were very Troublesome, and Trading very bad, and I having every year a Child, my Friends and Acquaintance pitied us, wondering how we Lived to pay such a rack Rent, and such a continual Charge;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132837:9"/> If they had <hi>known all,</hi> they might have wondered, for I have wondered my self; I paying to a Relation in the City sixteen Pounds a year, for seven years, for one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Eighty Pounds, the Interest thereof; and to keep my Promise with Tradesmen, I have paid the same Relat on several Times, for Eighteen Pounds, received in hand, twenty Pounds, paying it back at Twenty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a Week, which in sixteen years time I can charge my self with the paying of upwards of three hundred Pounds <hi>Interest-Mony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this sixteen years time I had fourteen Children; and one Miscarriage, a fit of Sickness on my self, which cost me upwards of Three Hundred Pounds, the last of my Physitians being the best he had in six Weeks time Fifty Pounds, besides Ten Pounds it cost me by-Charges. This Doctor was a <hi>Dear Joy,</hi> although an Ingenious man, his Name was <hi>Cray,</hi> living in St. <hi>Albans Street</hi> near St. <hi>James't Square,</hi> and he was an hundred and five years of Age when he Died. Now dear Fellow Traders, here comes the Pinch, for like the Distempers that are long breeding, either in Commonwealths, or Mans Body, when it breaks out, proves fatal to either, if not prevented by Providence. Thus it has been with me, I having an opportunity of removing out of the Rebellious place of the upper and lower <hi>Alsatia,</hi> and <hi>Sharp Island,</hi> vulgarly called by the name of <hi>White Fryars,</hi> meeting with a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as Fatal to me as my Landlady, his Name being upon Record, for an old Blind Bear, a Monster in Nature, who paid a Butcher once near two hundred pounds, he being so much Indebted to him in Contensious Law-Suits: If you would know more of him, he Married
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132837:9"/> one like himself, a Widow in <hi>Suffolk-Street,</hi> near <hi>Charing-Cross,</hi> which her Children are the worse for. I went that time the Circuit, into the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> with Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Allibone,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Powel,</hi> then Judges for that Assizes. I left it to my Wife to find out an House that she lik'd; and she, with some Acquaintance fixt on the House my Family now lives in; that is, the <hi>Sugar Loaf</hi> at <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Bar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I came off the Circuit, I liked the place, but thought it very dear, to pay one Hundred Pounds Fine, and to Repair all my self, which I was forc'd to do. As soon as I was entered here, I wanted nothing but a better and bigger House; The first year I had the Honour to dress the <hi>Serjeants Feast</hi> at <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> called, <hi>The Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>his Call of Serjeants.</hi> The same Summer I went the <hi>Oxford</hi> Circuit with Sir <hi>Thomas Powel,</hi> and Mr. Baron <hi>R.</hi> and famous Dr. <hi>Burgess</hi> went as far as <hi>Oxford</hi> with us; this being something remarkable by the Doctor's Preaching a Sermon there; where he took the Liberty to challenge the whole University about <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>his Son Isaac;</hi> which had it been a Popish Priest, he must not have gone off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Stripes. Another Observation I cannot omit, Baron <hi>R.</hi> going with the other Judge in the Morning to the <hi>Church,</hi> and in the Afternoon to a <hi>Conventicle</hi> in private. And in this Circuit I smelt a Rat; for I found all the Sheriffs to be <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> except the Sheriff of <hi>Salop,</hi> and great Doings, and a good profitable Circuit to me; but I found little Resort of the Old Protestant Gentlemen to our <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Sheriffs;</hi> but some <hi>Time serving Trencher Weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks,</hi> who are for that which is uppermost.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:132837:10"/>
               <p>When we came to <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> being the last Seat, the Judges had much a-do to make a Court, for want of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices, for many would not appear; some others were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of what was coming on; particularly, a Man of six pounds <hi>per annum</hi> was in the Town-Goal for Debt; so I had like to have been preferred to the <hi>Bench</hi> before I had been a <hi>Barrister,</hi> had I not other Fish to Fry in the Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</p>
               <p>These Fore boding I did not like; therefore when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Judges parted; the one, honest Sir <hi>Thomas Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> my constant Friend and Master, being always true to his Friend, and the best of Friends to me, went into <hi>Wales</hi> to his own Dwelling house; the other went privately out of Town, to prevent our being chargeable to him. For that Reason, to drive away that <hi>Spleen,</hi> I sent for All the Musick in the Town, and injoyed my self until Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas his Coach</hi> returned; Then I lived like Prince <hi>Dutton,</hi> and travelled home with Company of my own Kidney, without the Expence of one Farthing; which I cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit giving the Praise deserved, it being from my Fellow Servants in that Circuit.</p>
               <p>When I came home to the carefullest and best of Wives, I was received with that expected Joy that all good Wives will give to a careful industrious Husband, that is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful.</p>
               <p>Things of State began to gape for Change; and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> began to cry for <hi>Liberty and Property,</hi> which look'd like some dismal Change and Judgment from above, which soon after happened, I being a Fellow-Sufferer in these Disorders with the rest; all things of Government going off the Hinges; the dismal Hubbub of the <hi>Irish Massacree</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:132837:10"/> bellowing forth, my House was markt at, and as well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, had I not lived by an Eminent Neighbour, and good Friend, Mr. <hi>Child,</hi> my next Neighbour, considering <hi>Self preservation</hi> mixt withal, with the thought of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Oppression,</hi> I had a Guard in my House of the Trained Bands, which I almost fear'd as much as the <hi>Mobility,</hi> they proving no Security to <hi>Wild-Hoase;</hi> but like the <hi>Mice</hi> and <hi>the Wheesels</hi> in <hi>the Fable,</hi> they keeping off the poor Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and plundering the Place themselves.</p>
               <p>After this came out an Old Informer, one <hi>L.</hi> which in defence thereof cost me near Ten Pounds: Then that Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine was supprest by the Honoured Lord Chief Justice <hi>Holt,</hi> now Lord Chief Justice. Being full of business, and no want of Money, I left that <hi>K.</hi> my Tenant <hi>B.</hi> in my House in <hi>VVhite-Fryars,</hi> run in Arrears of Rent Forty Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Pounds, Taxes being allowed. This I could not get by Fair Means; I was forc'd to interceed with my Old Friend and Neighbour, then Sir <hi>Francis Child,</hi> one of the Sheriffs of <hi>London,</hi> to assist me in Forcing this Litigious Bruit to a Conformity; which Expedition that Day cost me near Fifteen Pounds, besides lik'd to be knockt on the Head by the <hi>Fryeronions;</hi> in which Action, them Villains giving more Ear to the <hi>Oppressor</hi> than <hi>the Oppressed;</hi> They and <hi>the Pack-Thread Council,</hi> a sort of Governours amongst them so called, wherein they did pass an Act, at a general Meeting, <hi>Nemine contra dicenti, That no Tenant should come into the House, whilst I was Landlord.</hi> Therefore I appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my self and Friends to the Saint my Landlady, whose Demand was so <hi>unreasonable,</hi> I was advised by my Friends to stand off, and pay not the Arrears of Rent, without she would comply at Reasonable Rates.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:132837:11"/>
               <p>This forc'd me to keep my own House for one Month until my Wife lay in of another Child; I was forc'd to come down into business, and comply with her Unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Demands, which was one Hundred and Forty Pounds for Five Years to come of the Lease, which I paid; which after the paying of an Hundred and Fifty Pounds at first, and a Rack-Rent of Sixty Three Pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for 16 years; I will be judged by any of the greatest of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, the <hi>Slubberdegullions,</hi> or any other of <hi>the Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick State menders</hi> (for from them <hi>I expect no mercy</hi>) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>they,</hi> or <hi>any other Traders but my self,</hi> that have, and <hi>ever had an aversion</hi> to any <hi>unjust</hi> or <hi>illegal proceeding,</hi> in what Nature so ever, would not have taken the Advantage of going lower down into the <hi>Fryars,</hi> when I was an <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant there,</hi> and <hi>made my own Terms:</hi> And if I had <hi>left her</hi> when I was <hi>her Servant,</hi> in one years time she would have been glad to have raken 50 <hi>l. per annum</hi> without a <hi>Fine:</hi> she Forgets the Kindness I did her, when after she turned off the Old <hi>Carret-pated, tender-footed, blockheaded, VVhiggish Lover,</hi> there came a <hi>brisk young Gallant,</hi> that sate up <hi>Night and Day with her,</hi> following the Old Proverb, <hi>how to court a VVidow.</hi> This <hi>Spark</hi> pretended he was Heir to 500 <hi>l.</hi> a year; which set <hi>her Fustiness</hi> mightily upon the Fret; but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>true and faithful Servant,</hi> made it my business to find it out; and found him to be only a Servant to one of the <hi>Prebends</hi> of <hi>VVindsor;</hi> which spoyl'd my Spark's <hi>Intrigue:</hi> but he went off with a <hi>Diamond Ring,</hi> for which she had a Tryal at Law with him at <hi>VVindsor;</hi> which may be seen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record.</p>
               <p>Now to my <hi>distress:</hi> When I had been at the Charge of removing these Goods to my House at <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132837:11"/> that was, as I have been credibly informed, and is still a <hi>a true shoving Friend</hi> of <hi>Ʋrsula</hi>'s. The she <hi>B</hi>'s Two Daughters, by the <hi>first Husband,</hi> brings a <hi>Replevy;</hi> I to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Suit, imploys <hi>two Attorneys,</hi> so called; one a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Romanist;</hi> the other, <hi>a City true blue Protestant;</hi> pays them Money before hand, being <hi>the sinews of the Law,</hi> in my Politicks, <hi>as well as the War,</hi> they have held me in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence these 3 years last <hi>March,</hi> to the Expence of 60 odd pounds; and all the satisfaction I have had, is <hi>a Writ of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,</hi> the last Term allow'd me, with Cost; when there is neither Goods nor Tenant to be found. And my <hi>two Petty Foggers;</hi> seeing I am going to imploy another, more honest than themselves, they send me a Bill, which by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Prothonitor,</hi> I have paid them too much already, which I shall have taxt this Term.</p>
               <p>In the next place, for my kindness to Relations, since I came to this House, it has cost me near one hundred and fifty Pounds, to Gentlemen, that I have not only lent them Mony to buy Shoos to their Feet, but trusted them; and to one particular, most Mony lent, which I have Bond for; Interest and Principle comes to, from each man, upwards of eighty Pounds, the Principle Mony being due near four years: Another, a Pillory Spark that formerly kept an Inn at <hi>R</hi>—when Sir <hi>Thomas Manby</hi> was High Sheriff, he having appeared with my Wife in the Taking of this House; for his Kindness in so doing, altho my Wife Paid him, he desired my Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in getting him in to be Bayliff of an Hundred, and being acquainted with the Under Sheriff, I was bound in a Bond of Five Hundred Pounds for his discharging this Trust, for which I paid in Mony, and what he was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132837:12"/> Indebted to me besides, upwards of Fifty Pounds: These Abuses and Disappointments, for my good Nature, drove me into a Passion of Extravagancy, beginning about three years since.</p>
               <p>In this time, amongst Strolers, Pipers, Harpers, Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merchants, with the little and great merry Grigs of the Town; not forgetting the many pretenders to Religion and Loyalty, especially one sly Forain Rogue, who drew me in to be Bound for him for thirty odd Pounds, and suffered me to be Sued for it, but I have him fast enough. This Conversation has cost me three hundred Pounds and more; which Mony I value not, for I would not be without the Knowing of the Vanity of my Fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in these and many other Discoveries, how they are Cullied by Bullies, Trapes, Sweetners, Sharpers and Jilts, which I have made trial of on a good Friend, and a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that I had a particular respect for; but I knew his blind side, he Loved, and was like the <hi>Hermet</hi> in the Fable, could not live much longer without a peice of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Flesh; I striking whilst the Iron was hot, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to be newly acquainted with one of the most Dexterous of her Function; and one, as it happened, that he never was acquainted with, which I wondered at, he being an old Whore-master about the Town, therefore he was the more Eager; which at first she Charm'd him; and altho it was <hi>Sunday,</hi> we must to some <hi>House of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment,</hi> which we agreed (being in <hi>Southwark</hi>) to <hi>Puntacks</hi> in the City; so, what with the Charming Voice and pretty Features, and witty Expressions, <hi>I found him fast,</hi> then I was well enough; next Morning betimes to his Lodgings I went to know his Pleasure: All business
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132837:12"/> was to be laid aside until he was better acquainted with this Lady, which I told him, <hi>I would manage for him;</hi> So I was got into an Office; Nothing like it in that <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi> When I came to the Ladies House that Morning, she askt about my Spark, of whom I gave her full satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that day we were to Dine with her at her own house, which was very well Furnisht with Good Plate, Jewels and other Furniture, to the Admiration of my Spark; then liv'd I beyond a <hi>German</hi> Prince, not without Mony, good Musick, Vocal and Instrumental, good Wine, good Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chairing and Coaching all day long: In a Months time, or there about, my Child, as I had Adopted her, and my self, had put my Gentleman to upwards of 50 pounds Expence. She borrowed 50 pounds of him, and my self 50 pounds more, and this all in the compass of 2 Months. Now if I could, at the first coming to this Office, draw an Old Gamester into this Priminary, what could not I do amongst the silly young Fry? But I am resolved to draw in no more, for I have heartily Repented of this; and to my abused Friend, which he is sensible of, that if I had not perswaded him off in time, she had grapled 50 <hi>l.</hi> more.</p>
               <p>The reason of my Exposing this in Print, is to give good Advice to all my fellow Christians; and to shew them what these Catterpillers, and Pesterers of Mankind, these Mercinary, Common, Jilting, Fulsom Women are; I have had the Experience of them Night and Morning, Drunk and Sober, and know the difference at Bed and Board, between a good Wife, and these Prostituted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Strumpets; I having sate Foot to Foot, with Bottle and Glass, Bill to Bill with some of the best of them: When
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132837:13"/> he that has Paid for what we Drank, has been denied Entrance, which Ingratitude is Natural to the Trade; therefore I not only wonder at all Mankind for this Folly, but particularly the Married Men, especially them that have Honest Women; Some Men I have heard say, <hi>The Women of the Town have such Charming ways with them;</hi> Why don't these Teach their Wives these ways? I am sure they may in a weeks time teach as much of that as will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them all their Life time, and more secure and safe from Distempers; therefore let me Advise you all from the highest to the lowest, to consider in time, for fear a worse thing befal you.</p>
               <p>I must relate to you, in the last year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign, I being then Constable in the Ward of <hi>Farringdon without,</hi> I was call'd to a Publick House in <hi>Water Lane,</hi> in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> there being <hi>Murder</hi> cryed out; when I came, we found a Gentleman-like Man on a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Town Dead, and she crying for help; the Account that was given by the Woman was this, <hi>The Gentleman being in Drink, picks her up in</hi> Fleetstreet, <hi>and goes into this House, where, not long after, he died upon her in that Condition;</hi> The Woman was sent to the House of Correction, and soundly Whipt. Now considerate Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would be in fear of such a Judgment as this, which is very true and remarkable.</p>
               <p>Now my Hand is in, I must give some <hi>particular advice</hi> to some of my <hi>Neighbours,</hi> of <hi>the Function;</hi> the first is, a famous <hi>upstart Aledraper</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> that is so proud grown, that <hi>I</hi> met him not long since in the City, and gave him the <hi>time of the day,</hi> but the <hi>pragmatical Fop</hi> took no notice of me; Another thing he has publickly declared in a Club that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132837:13"/> uses his House, <hi>That his Brewer takes of him 1500l. per annum,</hi> in which to my knowledge he is mistaken 2 parts in 3. As for his <hi>Burying place</hi> he has bought at <hi>Islington,</hi> 'tis well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. But, I hear <hi>he is turn'd Merchant;</hi> and I would have him advise with <hi>Aesop</hi>'s <hi>Shepherd turn'd Merchant;</hi> where in a Tempest he lost all his Figs, and thought it a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in saving his Life: That has been a <hi>fatal house</hi> 30 years since for <hi>unsetled Spirits;</hi> for I knew two successively, when they had got a great deal of Mony there, left that House for a bigger; One of them, to my knowledg, came into <hi>White-Fryers</hi> for shelter. The next, are two <hi>Neighbours</hi> in—<hi>Two famous Slubberdegullions,</hi> both, as I am credibly informed, <hi>guilty of Incest;</hi> one marrying Two Sisters, the other marrying One Sister, and making so much of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he has broke his Wife's Heart. I have a particular remark on that Villain at the Sign of the <hi>T</hi>—His shuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling with his Creditors, I need not trouble you withal; it has been publick enough several years since; and for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state he has got, you may judg how he has prosper'd; when I was <hi>Constable,</hi> a <hi>Common Female Diver</hi> met with a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in <hi>Fleetstreet,</hi> and went with him into a <hi>publick house,</hi> and there pickt his Pocket, and took from him to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of 40 <hi>l.</hi> or thereabouts: One <hi>Walker,</hi> a <hi>Porter,</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> came to me, and directed me to the House where the Gentlemans Pocket was pickt: <hi>I</hi> quickly made them find out the Strumpet; and when <hi>I</hi> had this Lady in my Custody, who should come to speak in her behalf but this Famous <hi>Sodomite,</hi> and was very angry with me that <hi>I</hi> would not <hi>take a Bribe, and let her go:</hi> For <hi>this Reason</hi> this <hi>Booby</hi> can never give me a good word. Perhaps <hi>they take it for Pride in me I</hi> do not associate <hi>my self with them.</hi> The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132837:14"/> Reason is, <hi>take them out of the Kitchen, they are fit for a Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden;</hi> Therefore to all <hi>sensible men I speak it;</hi> What great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Mortification is there, than the company of a hunching, pawming, mouthing, laughing, senseless boody, to a man of the meanest understanding, especially one that has been bred from his Cradle amongst Quality, and having lived in several of the best Families in the Kingdom, where I learned the Fundamental parts of <hi>Cookery,</hi> which is in plain <hi>English, good Housewifry;</hi> and if I have any Pride and Ambition in me, 'tis in keeping my betters, and them of sense and some understanding company, for there is something to be learned; when I am not my self I keep any Company comes to hand; therefore to all my fellow Creatures I speak it, from the highest to the lowest; With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your selves to your selves, into a Serious considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I have done for this two Months; altho it seem'd hard at first, I now would not change my resolution of Temperance, for the best Estate in the Kingdom; I find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my self free from frightful Dreams, extraordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance of Body, having the true tast of my Meat and Drink, and that received with a Gust; every part of my body keeping true motion, without disorder; the fragrancy of every Plant, the Harmony of the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, and other little Animals, beyond all the Scraping and Grimases of the Comaedians; being Natural, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fiction; besides in the place where I am, there are 3 such objects of Pity, 2 Men and a Woman, the two men, one that had an Estate of twelve hundred Pounds <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> an ingenious good Schollar, by the abuse of his Friends and Relations cheating of him, drove him into such a fit of Lunacy that he will never be himself, altho by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132837:14"/> an Oyl that the Dr. uses, that he learnt in his Travels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, he is much better than he has been; and to this Oyl I must give the praise, under God, of my Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and I think it worth its weight in Gold; which if it were not for the Caution of <hi>Aespo</hi>'s Ass in the Fable, Moral and Reflection, his putting on of the Lions Skin, I would Advise some of our City State-menders, to come and consider well what to do; but for fear of being whipt with my own lash, I'll leave off whilst I am well.</p>
               <p>The other man having too, upwards of one Thousand Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> got his Disorder by a Fit of Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and will never be fit to injoy the Estate, altho a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar too. The Woman's is Pride. One Remark that I have made in the Humour of the first man is, That he hates all Women, he being once in his youth Clapt by one, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he calls them all Pocky Whores; and ever since that, the finest Woman that is he will not come near. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Brother Libertines and Sinners, since the Religious of all sides have set us together by the Ears, let every one mend one; and as you are scandelized, and will not mind nor go to hear your Ministers, take the early Advice of one that has had the Theorick part, but more sensible of the Practick, in this loose debauched Age, and do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to <hi>Solomons</hi> Time, for fear God should not except your Repentance; but begin, as I have done, the <hi>3d</hi> Day of <hi>May,</hi> 1694, being my Birth-day, in the 48th year of my Age, the Day of the Invention or finding the Holy Cross, which this Day, and the Memory of the Passion of our Saviour, I have an extraordinary Devotion for, and ever had, when I minded any thing of Religion; begin
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132837:15"/> first with Morality, without which, Religion is <hi>Lunacy,</hi> and meer <hi>Banter;</hi> that care I have taken, I thank God, in setling and providing for my Family, that is, in renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lease of my House for 21 years to come, which I have done this 2 Months since: On this House I have laid out upwards of 3 hundred Pounds in Repairs and Improvements; I have left a Cook of my own Breeding up, that shall Dress a Dish of Meat as well as any Cook in or about the City of <hi>London,</hi> and other Servants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly that are fit for business; I have made over, and intrusted all this into the Hands of Capt. <hi>Johnson,</hi> my principal Creditor, whose kindness I shall never forget, in sending me to this place, whatever I have said of him in my passion; and he that will wrong such a Friend, as I am informed lately several hath him, it is pity the Law doth not make it Hanging, that is, when it's designed; and this that I have done, is not with design to Compound with any Creditor, or to defraud any one, for I have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as the Debts and Mony comes, to pay every Man twenty Shillings in the Pound; but my meaning is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve my Family, as it behoves every Christian so to do; I having exposed my self so publickly, and have suffered my self wilfully to be imposed on, when I could have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided it, which is no better than <hi>doing ill, that good might come on it,</hi> which I acknowledg a presumption in me; therefore as I have lashed out of my self, contrary to my Nature, and yet taken time by the Forelock, I would have others take warning by me, and avoid the giving the occasion of such jesting with Edg Tools, for a blot is no blot till its hit; but the Blur, as it hath been so publickly by me occasioned, as in Respect to the Religion I profess,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132837:15"/> I first desire the Indulgence thereof, and the Prayers of that Congregation in particular, and all good Christians in general, First, for the Scandal that I have given to all that pretend to Religion, or Civil Community; and that I may persevere to the end in this fully resolved undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which in the presence of God Almighty, I do with as true Contrition, and as heartily Discharge of the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance injoyned me, as if I was this Minute to depart this Life; and shall, if God permit me Health, and any Prosperity, endeavour to make such Satisfaction as my Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance shall allow; therefore, to lay a sure Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I may not faulter in this Pious Undertaking, I have resolved, and prepared, and setled my concerns ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, to withdraw my self into the Country for this <hi>Summer,</hi> where my Friends and Family shall, as often as the conveniency of the place will allow, hear from me.</p>
               <p>This I do against the consent of the principal part of my Creditors; but I do it with an intent to Habit my self to a more orderly Course of Life, I being not certain of my own Strength. Dear fellow Creatures, I conclude with a hearty concern for all that lead these vicious sort of Lives, for want of a serious Consideration, and their bellowing at the Government, which is only for more Plenty, that they may be more Riotous, I would Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise you to mend your Lives, and be Subject and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and live Peaceable under such Government as God Almighty permits to be over you, for that I have found all along most Peaceable; this I speak not to any in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, but to the general, especially them of my own perswasion, that are most Culpable, which hath often troubled me, to see them so constant at Chappel, and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132837:16"/> most wicked in Conversation; and them that I have been the most beholding to, for their <hi>Calumniating, Detracting,</hi> and <hi>Deceiving</hi> in general, which I pray God may forgive them, for I do. So hoping that some one may profit by my example, if so, I shall not think this last Week of time spent in this serious Work, to be ill bestowed, with my giving God the Glory in making me sensible of my past offences. I remain a well wisher to the <hi>English Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> antiently established by Law, since the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, against all <hi>Foraign Powers, Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Temporal;</hi> in an Hostile manner; and I desire that I, and my Family may be sheltered under the Wings of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> antiently Established, whom I have found my truest and best Friends.</p>
               <p>But being willing to Publish the most Pithy and sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reason of my withdrawing my self from my Family, with submission to the publick, I will venture a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Wilderness with <hi>Aesop</hi>'s Ass, but as near as I can, I will have a care of being beaten with my own Basting Ladle: The Reason is as followeth, I having Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried one of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I never liked her the worse, she being of the Old Stamp, and doth as she always did, live up to what she ever did pretend to, and that very Zealously when occasion has required. l keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Publick House, it is common Prudence to be civil and respectful to all People; but to some particularly, that I am, and have been obliged to, which it being not only Requisite, but grateful to appear in this Company, which if any Argument of News has presented, especially that which hath toucht my Loyalty, being despisingly deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Assertion falsly and Irreverendly grounded,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132837:16"/> and so Irreligiously managed, and especially upon the best of Masters, and truest of Friends; I have not had the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but to withdraw my self into some private room with Tears in my Eyes, and much ado to govern my self within the bounds of civil behaviour; but when I come to my self to consider my own offences, and others, is the occasion of it, it gives my great Soul and Loyal Spirits some relief, but it leaves a coolness in the Conversation after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; therefore as I have a natural Aversion to Hypocrisy even from the Duke, to the Linkman, I have taken the more positive resolution in this Affair, and when I can more freely command my own Labours, I may return again if God permit my Life so long; and altho I leave my All behind me, yet I carry <hi>Simonides</hi>'s Wealth in the Fable, after his Shipwrack, being contented in my Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, I leave the rest to Providence.</p>
               <p>Now I conclude with my last whim on the 3d of <hi>May,</hi> before mentioned, I prepared a Treat that came to nigh <hi>10l.</hi> with only <hi>1s.</hi> in my pocket; and to take leave of the Vanity and Extravagancy of the Age, I invited some <hi>Gentlemen of the Temple,</hi> that I have an <hi>Esteem for,</hi> and are not <hi>Reflected</hi> on in these <hi>Papers,</hi> and some <hi>Ladies,</hi> whose <hi>Conversation,</hi> I hope, proved not ungrateful to them, with a <hi>Consort of Musick,</hi> but I happened into a rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful House, which I chose for <hi>Privacy</hi> and <hi>Conveniency,</hi> which stopt me for a <hi>Reckoning</hi> of one and twenty Shillings, being part of the whole <hi>Reckoning,</hi> altho they had three times the value in <hi>Goods</hi> in and about their House that I brought in: This House, is a <hi>Wine-house</hi> near the Stables in <hi>Summerset House,</hi> by the Water side, where when the <hi>Porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> was Master; and living, I have drank the best of <hi>Port Wines;</hi> but now you may have as good in any <hi>Hedg Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:132837:17"/> in any part of the Town; <hi>I</hi> being forc'd to withdraw my self from my Company to <hi>consider what to do, I</hi> could have had 3 <hi>times the Mony of several in the Company,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> would not ask at such a time, <hi>when it would look like a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, to give Roast Meat, and beat them with the Spit.</hi> It was a great disappointment to lose that <hi>Conversation</hi> I so much delighted in; but I bore it patiently, knowing it the only means towards a Reformation; but the most sensible <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude</hi> was, I sent to one of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s cursed Mony Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in <hi>Gerard Street,</hi> a <hi>Black Boy</hi> without, and a very <hi>black Soul</hi> within (<hi>I</hi> am afraid) a parcel of Books, that I will not take <hi>10l.</hi> for them, to send what he thought fit, and his Mony to be repaid in a Month, with the Extortion of <hi>6d. per</hi> Month, for 20 Shillings; and he knows that he, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily has been not a little obliged to me. Another of our <hi>Catholick Crew,</hi> a Mealman, that at any time would take a Treat without Scruple of Conscience, but not one penny for me in my Necessity, but very sorry for my condition; my own Family the same: it being so, <hi>I</hi> will now <hi>look to my self, and live better than ever I have done, and free from Care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next, and last is my <hi>Advice to the Fair Sex in general;</hi> but first the <hi>Incumbered,</hi> that they would take care in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Lectures</hi> according to the <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of their <hi>Yoak mates Disorder,</hi> and at this time, mannage with <hi>diseretion;</hi> for many by their <hi>mismanagement</hi> make the <hi>Remedy worse than the Disease.</hi> This <hi>I</hi> am not willing to Enlarge too much upon, for fear of touching near home. As for the <hi>Merry Grigs,</hi> in all my Travels, <hi>I</hi> have found great Errors amongst them; <hi>I</hi> know but one that <hi>I</hi> have any <hi>Value</hi> for, she having been my best and most true Friend, which <hi>I</hi> cannot omit taking notice of; and indeed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132837:17"/> she is the most grateful and obliging of the whole Sex, and her <hi>Conversation</hi> is all that I ever coveted, but I am proud to be under her <hi>Command,</hi> which as far as I am capable, I shall, and ever will endeavour to be serviceable, she having been my most true Friend in my Necessity. I could make this Discourse much larger, but knowing the Temper of the Age, as not for reading large Books, I rest here,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Humble Servant,<lb/> and well Wisher,<lb/>
                     <hi>JOHN DƲTTON</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>Then farewel all you old Ingenious,</l>
                  <l>This ungrateful Age is so Abstenious,</l>
                  <l>That old Fashion'd <hi>Chaucers English,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Charmingly like Oracle spoke; Pish,</l>
                  <l>'Tis all Time and Labour lost; I could</l>
                  <l>Wish our Genius now were not so cold,</l>
                  <l>In not considering well our Future State,</l>
                  <l>But leave all Holy Practise till too late.</l>
                  <l>Our Learned <hi>Hudibras</hi> did foretel many</l>
                  <l>Accidents, that are our present Destiny;</l>
                  <l>In giving way to Swearing, Lying, Evil</l>
                  <l>Habits that are incourag'd by the Devil.</l>
                  <l>Precursers of that Antichristian Crew,</l>
                  <l>Who in their Nature will give none their due</l>
                  <l>Like Dog turn to his Vomit, laps up his spue,</l>
                  <l>Disloyal to their Maker, and were never true.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:132837:18"/>
               <p>If you would know more of an Impetuous Woman, look into <hi>Aesop</hi>'s Fable, Moral and Reflection, of <hi>Black-Birds</hi> and <hi>Thrushes;</hi> and another between the <hi>Taylor and his Wife,</hi> she calling him <hi>Prick louse;</hi> and when he duck'd her under water, that she could not speak, she acted her Part with nicking her Thumbs above the Water: This has been my case, and that too often, with Reflecting on Religion, which is a misfortune to Marry into a contrary Religion. All you that love your Peace, take pity on me, for this ungoverned Member in Woman, called the Tongue, which hath caused my taking rash Oaths, <hi>never to live with that which I only Loved;</hi> and I have not only said, but swore, <hi>never to Cohabit with her any more in this Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Think it very necessary to give an Account of my Behaviour since my resolved Reformation. To gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the whole, but more in particular, the most private Inquisitors into others manners and behaviour, and the most publick Neglecters of their own; I must confess, according to the publick Vogue of the World, there has been little sign of Amendment; but the reason is, the narrowness of my Circumstances hath prevented my Publishing this Work sooner; and having blasted my Credit, I can have nothing without the ready penny;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132837:18"/> and then my general Conversation hath been amongst some particular People of most Notorious Fame; the Age being very Censorious; altho in these matters, I must compare my self to be something like a Trunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, in making a great deal of Hammering, before I strike any Nail on the Head; indeed my Life hath been for these four years last past, a <hi>Farce,</hi> I having been pointed at as I have walked along the Streets, for a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and no Mad-man; a Prince, and no Prince, a <hi>Sotio,</hi> and no <hi>Sotio,</hi> a Libertine, and no Libertine, but the most like old <hi>Timon</hi> of all these; So that I am in a confusion within my self many times, whether I am Dead or Living; the whole Kingdom seems to me to be an Inchanted Island; when I seriously consider, I have prais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, that I have escap'd being put into <hi>Bedlam.</hi> If I speak a sensible word, it's Madness; if Swear, nay, say what I will, or carry my self with all the Sedateness possible, it is all Lunacy: So I am resolved to let the Jest go on, and make my self merry with the Thoughts of what hath past, and make my self as Easy, as my Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious will allow; for I must believe all my Writings and Protestations will be look'd upon but Panegyrick; and if it turns to my expected Benefit, I hope you will all in general give the Gainer leave to smile.</p>
               <p>I must desire all good People to judg Charitably of me, it being not in my power to subsist without the Conversation of a Witty, Cleanly, Airy Woman, altho indifferently Beautiful; for I look upon all Mankind of Sence, Health, and good Humour to be like the <hi>World,</hi> before it was Modelized, a Massy lump of Earth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conversation of Women: Do but consider all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132837:19"/> History, both Divine and Human, the Wisdom of God Almighty, in making Woman at second Thought, to try the Loyalty of Man, he proving false, Woman was made choice of; Then consider the great Atcheivements and Alterations in the World since its Creation; caused by Woman. I will not run too far on this Subject, for fear of running my self a ground; therefore farewel until the next occasion, which I hope will not happen on this Account.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132837:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>